Hello, and welcome to Lesson 36
您好 欢迎来到 Wolfram U
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
的微积分入门课程第 37 课。
The topic for this lesson is slope fields and Euler’s method.
本节课的主题是斜率场和欧拉法。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
先来简单介绍一下本课的内容。
The fact is that some differential equations
事实上，一些微分方程
are very difficult to solve by hand.
是很难用手解决的。
For example, here’s a differential equation that looks quite simple,
例如，这里有一个微分方程，看起来很简单。
y'[x] = y[x]^2 – x, and you want to solve it
y'[x]=y[x]^2 - x，你要解决的是
with the condition that when x = 1, then y = 0.
条件是当x=1时，则y=0。
Now the function DSolve can certainly solve this equation,
现在函数DSolve当然可以解这个方程。
but the solution is huge
办法总比困难多
and involves these so-called Bessel functions,
并涉及这些所谓的贝塞尔函数。
which occur in the oscillations of membranes and elsewhere.
其中发生在膜和其他地方的振荡。
In such cases, it is much easier to just visualize
在这种情况下，只需将以下内容可视化，就会轻松很多
what the solution to the curve looks like for any initial value.
对于任何初始值，曲线的解是什么样子的。
In this lesson, we’ll learn how to use slope fields
在本课中，我们将学习如何使用斜坡字段。
to see the behavior of such differential equations.
来观察这种微分方程的行为。
As an introduction to slope fields,
作为坡场的介绍。
let’s consider the differential equation y'[x] = f[x, y].
让我们考虑微分方程y'[x]=f[x，y]。
If you want to find the slope field for this equation,
如果你想找到这个方程的斜率场。
what you do is you plug in the values for x and y
您要做的是插入x和y的值。
in the function f and then plot the slope at that point.
函数f中，然后绘制该点的斜率。
What does that mean?
这意味着什么？
It means that you draw a small line segment
意思是说，你画一条小线段
with slope close to the value you get from the expression f[x, y].
斜率接近于表达式f[x，y]的值。
Then you get a slope field, which gives you a very general picture
然后，你会得到一个斜坡领域，这给你一个非常概括的画面。
of the solutions to the differential equation.
的微分方程的解。
It’s not very precise, but it’s good enough.
虽然不是很精确，但已经很好了。
Luckily we have two functions in the Wolfram Language.
幸运的是，我们在Wolfram语言中有两个功能。
There’s StreamPlot and VectorPlot, which can be used for this purpose.
有StreamPlot和VectorPlot，可以用来做这个用途。
For example, let’s go back to the earlier differential equation,
例如，我们再回到前面的微分方程。
and you can use VectorPlot by saying  over here,
你可以用VectorPlot说在这里。
or StreamPlot with the same kind of specification,
或具有相同规格的StreamPlot。
and you get back the vector field,
然后你就可以得到矢量场。
the slope field over here and the stream field over there.
坡地在这里，溪地在那里。
The stream field has a solution of curves
流场有曲线的解
instead of just the arrows like over here.
而不是像这里一样只有箭头。
Now in some cases, what we really want
在某些情况下，我们真正想要的是
are the particular solutions to a differential equation.
是微分方程的特殊解。
For example, in the first case for our introduction,
例如，在我们介绍的第一个案例中。
we had the differential equation with the initial value y[1] = 0.
我们有初始值为y[1]=0的微分方程。
To find that out, you can use the StreamPoints option like over here
要想知道，你可以使用StreamPoints选项，就像在这里一样
and get the particular solution curve
并得到特定的解曲线
on the vector plot or on the stream plot.
在向量图或流图上。
A couple more examples.
再举几个例子。
Here is the vector field for x – y, the stream plot.
这里是x-y的向量场，流图。
You see over here that when x is very large,
你看这边，当x很大的时候。
then you have a positive slope from the expression over here.
那么从这边的表达方式来看，你的斜率为正。
When y is very large, you have a negative slope.
当y非常大时，你的斜率为负。
The same thing can be worked out with VectorPlot over here
同样的事情也可以用VectorPlot来解决，在这里
with the initial value y[0] = 0.
初始值y[0]=0。
Okay. Another example.
好吧，又是一个例子。另一个例子。
Let’s take f to be x * y.
我们将f取为x*y。
Now what happens over here is the stream plot
现在这里发生的事情是流线图
depends upon where you are.
取决于你在哪里。
If you are in the first or the third quadrant,
如果你在第一或第三象限。
then both x and y are the same sign,
那么x和y都是同一个符号。
so you have positive slopes,
所以你有正斜率。
and just the opposite happens in the other two quadrants.
而其他两个象限的情况刚好相反。
If you want the particular solution y[1] = –1,
如果你想要特定的解y[1]=-1。
you plug that over here in StreamPoints
你把它插入到StreamPoints里
and you get back the plot for that particular curve.
然后你就可以得到那条特定曲线的图。
Okay. Now in practice, you might just want to estimate
好吧，现在在实践中，你可能只是想估算一下。现在，在实践中，你可能只是想估计一下。
the solution for a differential equation,
微分方程的解。
and that can be done with Euler’s method.
而这可以用欧拉的方法来完成。
The idea is this.
我的想法是这样的。
Here’s the same example from the introduction,
这也是介绍中的例子。
and you want to find the value at 2
而你想找到在2
starting with the value at 1 equal to 0.
从1处的值开始等于0。
What you do is you start with (1, 0)
你要做的就是从（1，0）开始。
and plug it in the slope over here, so the slope is –1.
并把它插在这边的斜率上，所以斜率是-1。
Then write down the linear approximation, which is y = –(x – 1).
然后写下线性近似值，即y=-(x-1)。
If you plug in 2, then the approximate value is –1.
如果你插上2，那么近似值就是-1。
But of course what you could do is
但你当然可以做的是
you could go off a little bit on the tangent line,
你可以在切线上走一下。
then change direction,
然后改变方向。
and then that will give you a better approximation.
然后会给你一个更好的近似值。
For example, you could go halfway from 1 to 2 up to 1.5,
比如说，你可以从1到2的一半到1.5。
and then you could change your direction with the new slope,
然后你可以用新的斜坡改变你的方向。
and you get a better approximation
而你会得到一个更好的近似值
from the linear approximation over here,
从这边的线性近似。
and you get back the solution at 2 to be –0.125.
而你得到的解决方案在2是-0.125。
Here’s the idea behind Euler’s method.
这就是欧拉方法的理念。
The idea is that when you take very short steps along tangent lines,
这个想法是，当你沿着切线走很短的步子。
you get much better estimates.
你会得到更好的估计。
Basically what you’ll do is
基本上你要做的是
you’ll use an equation of this type over here
你会用这样的公式来计算
where every value of y depends upon the previous value.
其中，y的每个值都取决于前一个值。
Here’s a visual for the case where y' = y and y[0] = 1.
以下是y'=y和y[0]=1的情况下的视觉效果。
Of course in this case, the exact solution is just e^x
当然在这种情况下，精确的解只是e^x。
because its derivative is itself.
因为它的导数就是自己。
If you have only one point, then you get back just a tangent line,
如果你只有一个点，那么你得到的只是一条切线。
the red line over here.
红线在这里。
If you take two points, you go halfway down,
如果你拿了两分，你就会半途而废。
then you change direction and you get a better approximation.
然后你改变方向，你会得到一个更好的近似值。
Then of course you could take three points, four points, et cetera.
那你当然可以拿三分，四分，等等。
By the time we get to ten points like the green line over here,
到了十点，比如这边的绿线。
then you get a really nice approximation.
那么你就会得到一个非常好的近似值。
Of course the top-most graph is the actual solution.
当然最上面的图是实际的解决方案。
With Euler’s method, the approximation improves
用欧拉法，近似度提高了。
as you take more and more points.
当你拿着越来越多的积分。
You have one point, then two points, then ten points
你有一个点，然后两个点，然后十个点
and then you get closer and closer to the solution.
然后你就会越来越接近解决方案。
Now Euler’s method relies on so-called recurrence relations.
现在欧拉的方法依靠的是所谓的递归关系。
What’s that?
那是什么？
Well, here’s the relation for Euler’s method, and what happens is
好吧，这是欧拉法的关系，发生了什么是
let’s say you want to find the value of y2—so n is 2.
假设你想求y2-所以n的值是2。
Then that depends upon y1 and x1.
那么这取决于y1和x1。
You need x1 and y1 to work out the value of y2.
你需要x1和y1来计算y2的值。
Then you say I don’t know the value of y1,
然后你说我不知道y1的值。
so to find the value of y1, you need the value of x0 and y0.
所以要找到y1的值，需要x0和y0的值。
But of course, those are just the initial conditions.
但当然，这些只是初始条件。
In practice, if you want to find, let’s say, y100,
在实践中，如果你想找到，比方说，y100。
you need to go around all the way to 0,
你需要绕过所有的方式到0。
and that’s of course a very tiresome thing to do by hand.
而这当然是一件非常烦人的手工活。
On the other hand, it’s a perfect thing to do by computer,
另一方面，这是一件完美的事情，用电脑来做。
so it’s very easy to program on a computer.
所以在电脑上编程非常容易。
After a couple of lessons, we’ll talk about how to make
上了几节课，我们就来谈谈如何让
a program that calculates the points from Euler’s method.
一个根据欧拉法计算点的程序。
That’s the end of this lesson, and the main point is
这节课到此结束，主要内容是
you can use slope fields to visualize
您可以使用斜率字段来可视化
the behavior of differential equations.
微分方程的行为。
We have two nice functions.
我们有两个不错的功能。
We have VectorPlot and we have StreamPlot to plot these slope fields.
我们有VectorPlot和StreamPlot来绘制这些坡度场。
You can use Euler’s method
你可以用欧拉的方法
to estimate the solution at various points,
以估计各点的解决方案。
and because that’s rather tedious to do,
而且因为这样做相当乏味。
we can actually program it with a computer,
我们其实可以用电脑编程。
but that you’ll learn very soon.
但你很快就会明白的
The next lesson is about separable differential equations.
下节课讲的是可分离微分方程。
Before we do that, do review today’s lesson.
在这之前，先做一下今天的复习。
It’s an important lesson for differential equations.
这是微分方程的重要一课。
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.
这节课到这就结束了 谢谢观看